[
    {
        "question": "which astronomer proposed the heliocentric theory in the 16th century",
        "answer": "nicolaus copernicus"
    },
    {
        "question": "the flag of which country holds the world record of being the oldest continuously used national flag",
        "answer": "denmark"
    },
    {
        "question": "which gas makes up more than 90 of mars atmosphere",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of lohars skills",
        "answer": "utter annihilation"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not king skill",
        "answer": "relief"
    },
    {
        "question": "who made the idea troy",
        "answer": "odysseus"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is another name for the black death that raged across the europe during the late middle ages",
        "answer": "yersinia pestis"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following juice is contained in the classic cocktail bloody mary",
        "answer": "tomato juice"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which city is denmarks statue of the little mermaid located",
        "answer": "copenhagen"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is chinas earliest known book of military strategy",
        "answer": "sun tzus the art of war"
    },
    {
        "question": "in greek mythology what was the name of hades 3headed dog which guarded the gates of the underworld",
        "answer": "cerberus"
    },
    {
        "question": "founder of edo bakufu",
        "answer": "tokugawa ieyasu"
    },
    {
        "question": "official measure martin luther",
        "answer": "edict of worms"
    },
    {
        "question": "which was a lighthouse built after macedonia conquered egypt and waste of the seven wonders of the ancient world",
        "answer": "the lighthouse of alexandria"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the last emperor of all russia",
        "answer": "nicholas ii"
    },
    {
        "question": "whose beauty is said to have been the cause of the trojan war",
        "answer": "helen"
    },
    {
        "question": "northern humanists like erasmus were most commonly known for what",
        "answer": "interest in religion and social form"
    },
    {
        "question": "which german psychologist discovered the human brains forgetting curve",
        "answer": "hermann ebbinghaus"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the conversion ratio of amperes a to milliamperes ma",
        "answer": "11000"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following did desiderius erasmus and thomas more have in common",
        "answer": "both were considered humanists"
    },
    {
        "question": "who first implemented the julian calendar in rome",
        "answer": "julius caesar"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is the worlds largest island",
        "answer": "greenland"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander signed a peace treaty with saladin in 1192",
        "answer": "richard i"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the first human woman created by hephaestus in greek mythology",
        "answer": "pandora"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander was in charge of capturing constantinople at the age of 21",
        "answer": "mehmed ii"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following fruits known as wolf peach were erroneously thought to be poisonous",
        "answer": "tomatoes"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was also known as the eastern roman empire",
        "answer": "byzantine empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following french kings was known as the sun king",
        "answer": "louis xiv"
    },
    {
        "question": "which inventor built the worlds first electric locomotive in 1837",
        "answer": "robert davidson"
    },
    {
        "question": "which type of holy sites grant troop attack bonuses",
        "answer": "flame altar"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following can not be found in alliance shops",
        "answer": "golden key"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is belisarius nickname",
        "answer": "last of the romans"
    },
    {
        "question": "which european countrys king funded christopher columbus famous expedition",
        "answer": "spain"
    },
    {
        "question": "from the 17th to 19th centuries the kingdom of prussia was mostly in which modern country",
        "answer": "germany"
    },
    {
        "question": "which mammalian order does suidae belong to",
        "answer": "artiodactyla"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was believed to be the prototype of king of hearts in poker",
        "answer": "charlemagne"
    },
    {
        "question": "what did spartacus do as a slave before leading the biggest slave rebellion of ancient rome",
        "answer": "a gladiator"
    },
    {
        "question": "who proposed the philosophical idea of i think therefore i am",
        "answer": "descartes"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following marine species has existed the longest",
        "answer": "nautilus"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country gave the statue of liberty ti american people as a gift",
        "answer": "france"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following physicists was born on the death anniversary of galileo galilei and died on the birth anniversary of albert einstein",
        "answer": "stephen hawking"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was called napoleon of crime in some of the sherlock holmes stories",
        "answer": "professor moriarty"
    },
    {
        "question": "which building was originally built in london to house the great exhibition of the works industry of all nations held in 1851",
        "answer": "the crystal palace"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was built at the order of shah jahan in the memory of his wife mumtaz mahal",
        "answer": "taj mhal"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many times is the character 1 used when you write from numbers 1 to number 99",
        "answer": "20"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which country did the carlist wars take place during the 19th century",
        "answer": "spain"
    },
    {
        "question": "which war was fought between the bristish houses of lancaster and york for the throne of england",
        "answer": "the wars of the roses"
    },
    {
        "question": "insufficient intake of which element may case thyromegaly",
        "answer": "iodine"
    },
    {
        "question": "official measure martin luther",
        "answer": "diet of worms"
    },
    {
        "question": "which french monarch was known as saint louis",
        "answer": "louis ix"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country in asia overlaps with the former parthian empire",
        "answer": "iran"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the softest material known to mankind",
        "answer": "talc"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was a knight of the round table",
        "answer": "lancelot"
    },
    {
        "question": "the three kingdoms of korea where baekje silla and",
        "answer": "goguryeo"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a nonrenewable energy source such as coal oil or natural gas",
        "answer": "fossil fuel"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is an alternative energy source based on splitting heavy atoms into lighter ones to release energy",
        "answer": "nuclear energy"
    },
    {
        "question": "which war ended the rule of the house of plantagenet and began the rule of the tudors in england",
        "answer": "the wars of the roses"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is named death hydromel",
        "answer": "sarka"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these is not a natural resource",
        "answer": "clothing"
    },
    {
        "question": "the punic wars were fought by ancient rome and what other ancient empire",
        "answer": "ancient carthage"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the last female pharaoh of the ptolemy dynasty",
        "answer": "cleopatra vii"
    },
    {
        "question": "raphael is best known for his creation of which of the following",
        "answer": "school of athens"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many phases are there in the mightiest governorevent",
        "answer": "5"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is known as kamakuras warlord",
        "answer": "minamoto no yoshitsune"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these is used to rally alliance troops",
        "answer": "castle"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the highest level a city hall can reach in rise of kingdoms",
        "answer": "25"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country started the tradition of the 8hour workday",
        "answer": "united kingdom"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was not invented in china",
        "answer": "seismographs"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country is not in europe",
        "answer": "egypt"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commanders excels at attacking enemy cities",
        "answer": "caesar"
    },
    {
        "question": "while gutenberg introduced the printing press in europe his invention was influenced by which country the first to develop a moveable type",
        "answer": "china"
    },
    {
        "question": "the four major varieties of guzheng in ancient china were the haozhong luqi jiaowei and the",
        "answer": "raoliang"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of el cids skills",
        "answer": "chivalry"
    },
    {
        "question": "with whom did minamoto no yoshitsune raise an army to fight taira no kiyomori",
        "answer": "minamoto no yoritomo"
    },
    {
        "question": "what color is a polar bears skin",
        "answer": "black"
    },
    {
        "question": "egyptians made paper from which material",
        "answer": "papyrus"
    },
    {
        "question": "the differences among a species like different bird beaks are called",
        "answer": "variations"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the length of a marathon in kilometers",
        "answer": "422 km"
    },
    {
        "question": "which part of the brain will alcohol affect",
        "answer": "the cerebellum"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the troop health bonus you can get from a fully upgraded hospital",
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "what are the books of covenant used for",
        "answer": "upgrading castle"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many elite commanders are there in the game",
        "answer": "5"
    },
    {
        "question": "the three great philosophers of ancient greece were plato aristotle and",
        "answer": "socrates"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following can not be found in a silver chest at the tavern",
        "answer": "lvl 3 tome of knowledge"
    },
    {
        "question": "which unit type is strong against archers",
        "answer": "cavalry"
    },
    {
        "question": "which unit type is strong against cavalry",
        "answer": "infantry"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is the commander considered an enemy of rome since childhood",
        "answer": "hannibal barca"
    },
    {
        "question": "who painted the last supper",
        "answer": "leonardo da vinci"
    },
    {
        "question": "ancient egyptian history spans how many kingdoms",
        "answer": "3  old middle new"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is the king of the kingdom",
        "answer": "leader of the alliance that conquers the lost temple"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not a characteristic of renaissance art",
        "answer": "flattwodimensional"
    },
    {
        "question": "which famous and influential family did the famous renaissance art patron duke lorenzo belong to",
        "answer": "medici"
    },
    {
        "question": "wealthy family in florence",
        "answer": "medicis"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was not a pillar of the renaissance",
        "answer": "mannerism"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was a renaissance intellectual movement in which thinkers studied classical texts and focused on human potential and achievements",
        "answer": "humanism"
    },
    {
        "question": "which period of european history lasting from 1300 to 1600 saw renewed interest in classical culture and led to farreaching changes in art learning and views of the world",
        "answer": "renaissance"
    },
    {
        "question": "without using buffs how many action points can a governor have",
        "answer": "1000"
    },
    {
        "question": "which unit strong against infantry",
        "answer": "archer"
    },
    {
        "question": "hich of the following commanders excels at leading calvary",
        "answer": "minamoto no yoshitsune"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following does not award individual credits",
        "answer": "giving resources to allies"
    },
    {
        "question": "which portuguese explorer sailed from the cape of good hope to india",
        "answer": "vasco de gama"
    },
    {
        "question": "why do frogs and other organisms produce so many eggsoffspring",
        "answer": "the more offspring produced the more likely they will survive"
    },
    {
        "question": "what are arrows of resistance used for",
        "answer": "upgrading watch tower"
    },
    {
        "question": "renaissance painters in flanders as in italy tended to produce what type of artwork",
        "answer": "realistic"
    },
    {
        "question": "what provided the major economic support for the renaissance",
        "answer": "wealthy patrons"
    },
    {
        "question": "why are advantageous traits more likely to be passed onto offspring",
        "answer": "because they are more likely to survive and produce"
    },
    {
        "question": "after its foundation in the 6th century bce which institution of the roman republic served as a consultative parliament",
        "answer": "the senate"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the name for electricity produced by water power using large dams in a river",
        "answer": "hydroelectric power"
    },
    {
        "question": "the process of splitting atoms is known as",
        "answer": "fission"
    },
    {
        "question": "santa claus travels on a sleigh pulled by what animal",
        "answer": "reindeer"
    },
    {
        "question": "which war was fought between british houses of lancaster and york for the throne of england",
        "answer": "the wars of the roses"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these was the only commander to defeat cyrus the great in battle",
        "answer": "tomyris"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commanders joined a rebellion against her own husband",
        "answer": "constance"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is nicknamed the roaring barbarian",
        "answer": "lohar"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following resources cannot be found in your jeans",
        "answer": "lead"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander was paired with minamoto",
        "answer": "tomoe gozen"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was a general during japans genpei war",
        "answer": "tomoe gozen"
    },
    {
        "question": "in greek mythology to whom did paris the prince of troy give golden apple inscribed with to the most beautiful goddess",
        "answer": "aphrodite"
    },
    {
        "question": "of the 12 chinese zodiac animals which comes first",
        "answer": "rat  mouse"
    },
    {
        "question": "which civilization was the first to have public toilets",
        "answer": "ancient rome"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a fossil fuel formed from marine organisms that is often found in folded or tilted layers and used for heating and cooking",
        "answer": "natural gas"
    },
    {
        "question": "from the 8th to the 11th century ce what did europeans frequently call the scandinavian invaders who frequently ravaged their lands",
        "answer": "vikings"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is an inexhaustible energy resource that relies on hot magma or hot dry rocks below ground",
        "answer": "geo"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is considered an energy source",
        "answer": "petroleum"
    },
    {
        "question": "the renaissance was a rebirth of",
        "answer": "classical culture"
    },
    {
        "question": "advantages of johannes gutenbergs printing press include all of the following except",
        "answer": "increase in church power"
    },
    {
        "question": "who invented the printing press",
        "answer": "johann gutenberg"
    },
    {
        "question": "who founded the kingdom of asturias",
        "answer": "pelagius"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following does not give commanders exp",
        "answer": "attacking other players"
    },
    {
        "question": "raphael is best known for",
        "answer": "school of athens"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a phase of the mightiest governor",
        "answer": "enemy elimination"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these two were created by leonardo da vinci",
        "answer": "the last supper mona lisa"
    },
    {
        "question": "which war was fought between the british",
        "answer": "war of roses"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is nicknamed carthages guardian",
        "answer": "hannibal barca"
    },
    {
        "question": "what two major works are attributed to homer",
        "answer": "the odyssey and the iliad"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not an objective of greek mythology",
        "answer": "provide a path for salvation"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is nicknamed the father of conquest",
        "answer": "baibars"
    },
    {
        "question": "where do most hurricanes start",
        "answer": "on the open seas"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is known as the lady of the mercians",
        "answer": "thelfld"
    },
    {
        "question": "which landmark in sydney australia is shaped like sails",
        "answer": "sydney opera house"
    },
    {
        "question": "egypts economy was primarily based on what",
        "answer": "agriculture"
    },
    {
        "question": "which planet in our solar system rotates the fastest",
        "answer": "jupiter"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commanders was part of the battle of red cliffs",
        "answer": "cao cao"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is julius caesars nickname",
        "answer": "uncrowned king"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many fingers does the cartoon character mickey mouse have on each hand",
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "which portuguese explorer was the first european to sail to the southern tip of africa",
        "answer": "bartolomeu dias"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which country was air conditioning invented",
        "answer": "usa"
    },
    {
        "question": "the two capitals of austria  hungary were budapest and",
        "answer": "vienna"
    },
    {
        "question": "in greek mythology what is the relationship between zeus and hermes",
        "answer": "father and son"
    },
    {
        "question": "in greek mythology which hero requested for the golden fleece",
        "answer": "jason"
    },
    {
        "question": "the end justifies the means was a key belief of the author of the prince what was his name",
        "answer": "machiavelli"
    },
    {
        "question": "where did the renaissance begin",
        "answer": "italy"
    },
    {
        "question": "who painted the mona lisa",
        "answer": "leonardo da vinci"
    },
    {
        "question": "movable type was first used in which country",
        "answer": "china"
    },
    {
        "question": "the windsor knot was made popular by which king of england",
        "answer": "edward viii"
    },
    {
        "question": "which ancient greek scholar laid the foundations for future european mathematics and authored the elements of geometry",
        "answer": "euclid"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the only king of england to be executed",
        "answer": "charles i"
    },
    {
        "question": "what four words saying did oda nobunaga live by",
        "answer": "rule with absolute force"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not a reason why the renaissance began in italy",
        "answer": "the black plague did not hit italy as a result of the alps"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not an objective of greek mythology",
        "answer": "provide path of salvation"
    },
    {
        "question": "under normal circumstances which layer of the sun can we see with the naked eye",
        "answer": "photosphere"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is known as barbarossa",
        "answer": "frederick i"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following does the green olympic ring represent",
        "answer": "oceania"
    },
    {
        "question": "which ancient greek physicist famously discovered the concept of buoyancy while taking a bath",
        "answer": "archimedes"
    },
    {
        "question": "how do you get alliance technology credits",
        "answer": "by donating to the alliance"
    },
    {
        "question": "egypts economy was primarily based on",
        "answer": "agriculture"
    },
    {
        "question": "in greek mythology what was achilles only weak point",
        "answer": "his heel"
    },
    {
        "question": "mutations are a change in what",
        "answer": "dna"
    },
    {
        "question": "which honorary rank was the founder of kentucky fried chicken kfc given",
        "answer": "colonel"
    },
    {
        "question": "which citystate of ancient greece was known for its brutal military training and bravery",
        "answer": "sparta"
    },
    {
        "question": "wales officially became part of the kingdom of great britain during the reign of which king",
        "answer": "king henry viii"
    },
    {
        "question": "queen victoria of england was part of which royal house",
        "answer": "the house of hanover"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the seven wonders of the world were created to cure the new queen of babylons homesickness",
        "answer": "the hanging gardens"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a nonrenewable energy source",
        "answer": "water"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander was considered an enemy of rome from an early age",
        "answer": "hannibal barca"
    },
    {
        "question": "which art group is known as a national treasure of canada",
        "answer": "cirque du soleil"
    },
    {
        "question": "which roman emperor was named augustus after ending a civil war",
        "answer": "gaius octavius"
    },
    {
        "question": "in norse mythology who wielded the weapon gungnir",
        "answer": "odin"
    },
    {
        "question": "northern humanists like erasmus were most commonly known for what",
        "answer": "the religions"
    },
    {
        "question": "during the renaissance why was florence significant",
        "answer": "birthplace of the renaissance"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following describes a monotheist",
        "answer": "someone who warships 1 god"
    },
    {
        "question": "to whom did india give title mahatma",
        "answer": "mohandas karamchand gandhi"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many action points can a governor have",
        "answer": "1000"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a name for sedimentary rock formed from decayed plant materiel in swampy areas",
        "answer": "coal"
    },
    {
        "question": "ashoka the great was the king of which ancient indian kingdom",
        "answer": "maurya"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which continent is the human race generally thought to have originated",
        "answer": "africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the name of the renewable energy derived from burning organic materials such as wood and alcohol",
        "answer": "biomass energy"
    },
    {
        "question": "where did king louis xiv of france move the royal court to in 1682",
        "answer": "palace of versailles"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the emperor of the first french empire",
        "answer": "napoleon bonaparte"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commanders excels at leading archers",
        "answer": "yi seonggye"
    },
    {
        "question": "who founded the joseon dynasty",
        "answer": "yi seonggye"
    },
    {
        "question": "first general of the edo shogunate",
        "answer": "tokugawa ieyasu"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the center of a hurricane called",
        "answer": "eye"
    },
    {
        "question": "which prominent statesman served as the first general of the edo shogunate at the end of japans warring states period",
        "answer": "tokugawa ieyasu"
    },
    {
        "question": "in ark of osiris where are you supposed to take the ark",
        "answer": "escort the ark to a nonenemy building"
    },
    {
        "question": "which group conquered the byzantine empire",
        "answer": "the ottomans"
    },
    {
        "question": "where was the rallying point for the first crusade",
        "answer": "constantinople"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a term for a valuable material of geologic origin that can be extracted from the earth",
        "answer": "natural resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "which city hosted the 2000 summer olympics",
        "answer": "sydney"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a liquid fossil fuel formed from marine organisms that is burned to obtain energy and used to manufacture plastics",
        "answer": "oil"
    },
    {
        "question": "who killed hector and how achilles die",
        "answer": "achilles arrow though his heel"
    },
    {
        "question": "first created in ancient greece to which profession does hippocratic oath apply",
        "answer": "doctors"
    },
    {
        "question": "who instituted the julian calendar",
        "answer": "julius caesar"
    },
    {
        "question": "who owned everything in ancient egyptian kingdoms",
        "answer": "pharaoh"
    },
    {
        "question": "which part of the human body contains mostly water",
        "answer": "eyeballs"
    },
    {
        "question": "before leading the biggest slave rebellion of ancient rome what was spartacus",
        "answer": "gladiator"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the champion keiras nickname",
        "answer": "the red chameleon"
    },
    {
        "question": "ashoka the great was the king of which ancient kingdom",
        "answer": "maurya dynasty"
    },
    {
        "question": "which artist designed st peters basilica in the vatican",
        "answer": "michelangelo"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was praised by his countryman as ancient greeces best and most honest democratic representatives",
        "answer": "pericles"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the name of the revolution in 1688 which established the british constitutional monarchy",
        "answer": "glorious revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "which part of the brain will alcohol affect",
        "answer": "cerebellum"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the emperor of the first french empire",
        "answer": "napoleon bonaparte"
    },
    {
        "question": "the process of combining atoms is known as what",
        "answer": "fusion"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of pelagius passive skills",
        "answer": "charge"
    },
    {
        "question": "which prominent statesman served as the first general of the edo shogunate at the end of japans warring states period",
        "answer": "tokugawa ieyasu"
    },
    {
        "question": "which was the only ancient civilization to develop in a tropical jungle rather than a river basin",
        "answer": "the incas"
    },
    {
        "question": "which ethnic group founded the earliest civilization of mesopotamia",
        "answer": "the sumerians"
    },
    {
        "question": "the coneshaped winds of tornadoes are notable for doing what",
        "answer": "spinning"
    },
    {
        "question": "who commanded the new model army founded by parliament during the english civil war",
        "answer": "cromwell"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is considered the father of modern olympic games",
        "answer": "pierre de coubertin"
    },
    {
        "question": "when is the declaration of independence",
        "answer": "1776"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the first emperor of rome",
        "answer": "gaius octavius augustus"
    },
    {
        "question": "unit type strong against infantry",
        "answer": "archer"
    },
    {
        "question": "where did king louis xiv of france move to royal court to in 1682",
        "answer": "palace of versailles"
    },
    {
        "question": "which beverage was invented by american pharmacist john pemberton",
        "answer": "cola"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commander excels at gathering resources",
        "answer": "cleopatra vii"
    },
    {
        "question": "the more genetic variation a population has the more likely it is that some individual will what",
        "answer": "survive"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commanders excels at leading infantry",
        "answer": "richard i"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was an enemy of richard the lionheart",
        "answer": "saladin"
    },
    {
        "question": "in greek mythlogy which hero quested for the golden fleece",
        "answer": "jason"
    },
    {
        "question": "which landmark in sydney australia is shaped like sails",
        "answer": "opera house"
    },
    {
        "question": "where do adaptations come from",
        "answer": "both mutations and genetic recombination"
    },
    {
        "question": "where did genghis khan start building his mongolian empire",
        "answer": "asia"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the founder of the mongolian empire",
        "answer": "genghis khan"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the name for the phenomenon by which organisms that are better adapted to the environment survive to pass traits to their offspring",
        "answer": "natural selection"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commanders was part of the hundred years war",
        "answer": "joan of arc"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander was nicknamed mead of death",
        "answer": "sarka"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is a monotheist",
        "answer": "only believe in one god"
    },
    {
        "question": "what discovery made the deciphering of hieroglyphics possible",
        "answer": "rosetta stone"
    },
    {
        "question": "eyeglasses are composed of quartz sand and what",
        "answer": "petroleum"
    },
    {
        "question": "when achilles refuses to fight patroclus puts on achilles armor fights the trojans and dies who is patroclus killed by",
        "answer": "hector"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which year did richard and saladin sign a truce",
        "answer": "1192"
    },
    {
        "question": "mutations are important because they bring about what",
        "answer": "genetic variation needed for a population to evolve"
    },
    {
        "question": "in ark of osiris which speedup can be used",
        "answer": "healing speed up"
    },
    {
        "question": "how did saladin change the middle east",
        "answer": "palestine"
    },
    {
        "question": "when was the declaration of independence written",
        "answer": "1776"
    },
    {
        "question": "the mughal empire carried islam to where",
        "answer": "most of india"
    },
    {
        "question": "which musical instrument has six strings",
        "answer": "guitar"
    },
    {
        "question": "the four biggest musicals in the world are cats les miserables miss saigon and",
        "answer": "the phantom of the opera"
    },
    {
        "question": "france and germany were both once part of what feudal kingdom",
        "answer": "francia"
    },
    {
        "question": "in russian history what nickname was the first tzar given for their tyranny",
        "answer": "ivan the terrible"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is considered a metallic resource",
        "answer": "iron"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is known as the conqueror of chaos",
        "answer": "cao cao"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the babylonian codes of law was the first full set of written laws in recorded history",
        "answer": "the code of hammurabi"
    },
    {
        "question": "which european wrote the first travelogue detailing chinas history culture and art",
        "answer": "marco polo"
    },
    {
        "question": "chinas crosstalk sketch comedy format originates in three places tianqiao in beijing the quanty bazaar in tianjin and where in nanjing",
        "answer": "fuzimiao"
    },
    {
        "question": "homers the iliad focuses on events happening during which war or battle",
        "answer": "the trojan war"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not part of mexicos flag",
        "answer": "camel"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander was known as the celtic rose",
        "answer": "boudica"
    },
    {
        "question": "which type of natural disaster is measured using the richter scale",
        "answer": "earthquake"
    },
    {
        "question": "which is recognized by the guinness book of world records as having the largest cumulative circulation of any singleauthor comic",
        "answer": "eiichiro oda  one piece"
    },
    {
        "question": "in ancient greece which philosopher liked to discuss ideas on a street which then got the nickname peripatetic school",
        "answer": "aristotle"
    },
    {
        "question": "galileos leaning tower of pisa experiment overturned a theory of which ancient greek scientists",
        "answer": "aristotle"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander showed their military genius in the battle of poitiers in the 8th century ad",
        "answer": "charles martel"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander showed their military genius in the battle of tours in the 8th century ad",
        "answer": "charles martel"
    },
    {
        "question": "where did the soldiers of ancient rome get their weapons and armor",
        "answer": "themselves"
    },
    {
        "question": "who wrote the art of war",
        "answer": "sun tzu"
    },
    {
        "question": "during the trojan war which greek warrior killed hector",
        "answer": "achilles"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is zeus elder brother in geek mythology",
        "answer": "poseidon"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following serves as the national flower of the philippines",
        "answer": "sampaguita"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the name for electricity produced by water using large dams in a river",
        "answer": "hydroelectric energy"
    },
    {
        "question": "whose autobiography living to tell the tale won them the nobel prize in literature",
        "answer": "gabriel garca mrquez"
    },
    {
        "question": "which official measure made it a crime to give martin luther food or shelter",
        "answer": "edict of worms"
    },
    {
        "question": "which ancient civilization built the lost city of machu picchu",
        "answer": "the incas"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these cities hosted the olympics in 1900",
        "answer": "paris"
    },
    {
        "question": "the taj mahal was built during which indian dynasty",
        "answer": "the mughal dynasty"
    },
    {
        "question": "which emperor issued the proclamation of milan",
        "answer": "constantine i"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following achievements must be completed before the special snowflake achievement",
        "answer": "longrange strike"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is commander lancelot good at",
        "answer": "leading cavalry units"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is commander baybars good at",
        "answer": "leading cavalry units"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is commander hermann good at",
        "answer": "leading archers"
    },
    {
        "question": "when a governors city hall reaches level 25 how many farms can they build",
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is commander keira good at",
        "answer": "leading archers"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is commander osman i good at",
        "answer": "attacking cities"
    },
    {
        "question": "which buff can be acquired from occupying a sanctum of courage",
        "answer": "increase exp gained by commanders"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the commander hannibal barca good at",
        "answer": "attacking cities"
    },
    {
        "question": "who came up with the trojan horse idea",
        "answer": "odysseus"
    },
    {
        "question": "who won the trojan war",
        "answer": "the greeks"
    },
    {
        "question": "old part empire now on which asian country lands",
        "answer": "iran"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is commander eulji mundeok good at",
        "answer": "leading infantry units"
    },
    {
        "question": "what causes lunar eclipses",
        "answer": "the earth moves directly between the sun and the moon"
    },
    {
        "question": "during the second punic war in which battle did a vastly outnumbered hannibal defeat a roman army",
        "answer": "the battle of cannae"
    },
    {
        "question": "the end justifies the means was a key belief of the author of the prince what was his name",
        "answer": "machiavelli"
    },
    {
        "question": "one day on the planet venus is approximately equal to how many earth days",
        "answer": "243 days"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following nations is the closest to the north pole",
        "answer": "finland"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of the major greenhouse gases in earths atmosphere",
        "answer": "nitrogen"
    },
    {
        "question": "what was another usage of gin aside from being a popular drink in the 18th century",
        "answer": "medicine"
    },
    {
        "question": "when catching and releasing deep sea fishwhy is it important to pierce their swim bladder",
        "answer": "to prevent them from dying of distended swim bladders"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following factors allows certain mixed drinks to be layered",
        "answer": "density"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following cat breeds is known for being hairless",
        "answer": "sphynx"
    },
    {
        "question": "when is the international day of forests",
        "answer": "march 21"
    },
    {
        "question": "when is the world no tobacco day",
        "answer": "may 31"
    },
    {
        "question": "when did dinosaurs first exist",
        "answer": "triassic"
    },
    {
        "question": "which nation was not involved in the battle of waterloo",
        "answer": "italy"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is commander sun tzu good at",
        "answer": "leading city garrisons"
    },
    {
        "question": "the air often feels fresher after a thunderstorm because it has been enriched with which gas",
        "answer": "ozone"
    },
    {
        "question": "the great asoka which was the king of the ancient indian kingdom",
        "answer": "maurya"
    },
    {
        "question": "who came up with the trojan horse idea who won the trojan war",
        "answer": "odysseus the greeks"
    },
    {
        "question": "which one of the following is not one of hermanns skills",
        "answer": "irresistible"
    },
    {
        "question": "keira once defied the worlds expectations about her in a glorious battle where did this battle take place",
        "answer": "sunset canyon"
    },
    {
        "question": "chinas temple of heaven was built during the reign of which emperor",
        "answer": "the yongle emperor zhu di"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of keiras skills",
        "answer": "unruly blood"
    },
    {
        "question": "the kingdom title queen increases which of the following",
        "answer": "gathering speed"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many bones does an adult human have",
        "answer": "206"
    },
    {
        "question": "who funded christopher colombuss travels",
        "answer": "spain"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the first of henry viiis children to rule england",
        "answer": "edward vi"
    },
    {
        "question": "henry i took the throne of englnd in the year 1100 after which relative died",
        "answer": "his brother"
    },
    {
        "question": "what causes the distinctive smell in the air after it rains",
        "answer": "the influence of actinomycetes"
    },
    {
        "question": "of the following nations which has the smallest area",
        "answer": "vatican city"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the hardest part of the human body",
        "answer": "tooth enamel"
    },
    {
        "question": "in most cases what kind of mosquitoes will drink animal blood",
        "answer": "female mosquitos"
    },
    {
        "question": "which historical figure is entombed in palenques temple of the inscriptions",
        "answer": "pakal the great"
    },
    {
        "question": "where did king john of england agree to the magna carta in 1215",
        "answer": "runnymede"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is an accurate description of the mediterranean climate",
        "answer": "hot dry summers and cool wet winters"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of osman is skills",
        "answer": "oblique tactics"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of belisarius skills",
        "answer": "thunderous force"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following kingdom title descriptions are incorrect",
        "answer": "prime minister has increased troop attack"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the commander view page what buff do commanders acting as a drillmaster get",
        "answer": "1 troop attack"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the commander view page  what buff do commanders acting as a ranger get",
        "answer": "5 xp gain  damage vs barbarians none of these answers"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the commander view page  what buff do commanders acting as a tax officer get",
        "answer": "5 gathering speed"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the commander view page  what buff do commanders acting as a iron guard get",
        "answer": "1 troop health"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the commander view page  what buff do commanders acting as a supply captain get",
        "answer": "5 gathering speed and troop load"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the commander view page  what buff do commanders acting as a charge captain get",
        "answer": "1 rally attack  rally troop march speed"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the commander view page  what buff do commanders acting as a king head get",
        "answer": "1 troop defense and health"
    },
    {
        "question": "where was commander lohar born",
        "answer": "in a remote barbarian tribe"
    },
    {
        "question": "of the below commanders which is best suited to lead troops against infantry enemies",
        "answer": "hermann"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was praised by his countrymen as ancient greeces best and most honest democratic representative",
        "answer": "pericles"
    },
    {
        "question": "of the below commanders which is best suited to lead troops against archer enemies",
        "answer": "cao cao"
    },
    {
        "question": "of the below commanders which is best suited to lead troops against cavalry enemies",
        "answer": "sun tzu"
    },
    {
        "question": "of the below commanders which is best suited to lead troops when gathering resources",
        "answer": "seondeok"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which country is the mysterious stonehenge located",
        "answer": "united kingdom"
    },
    {
        "question": "in chinas han dynasty who opened the silk road on the orders of emperor wu",
        "answer": "zhang qian"
    },
    {
        "question": "why was scurvy once a common problem for sailors",
        "answer": "a lack of fresh fruit and vegetable on long voyages"
    },
    {
        "question": "why does drinking coffee make people feel more awake",
        "answer": "it contains caffeine"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following illnesses can be caused by a lack of vitamin d",
        "answer": "rickets"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commanders excels at leading cavalry",
        "answer": "minamoto no yoshitsune"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which year did richard the lionheart and saladin sign a truce",
        "answer": "1192"
    },
    {
        "question": "which is not a king skill",
        "answer": "relief"
    },
    {
        "question": "what outstanding contribution to science won biologist karl landsteiner the nobel prize",
        "answer": "discovering the human blood groups"
    },
    {
        "question": "in most cases which kind of lion has a mane",
        "answer": "adult male"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the location of the mysterious stoneage",
        "answer": "germany"
    },
    {
        "question": "what was the relationship between the famed generals tolui and genghis khan",
        "answer": "father and son"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following vitamins is most helpful for maintaining good vision",
        "answer": "vitamin a"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following kingdom title descriptions are incorrect",
        "answer": "dukes have increased troops attack"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the main purpose of white blood cells in the human body",
        "answer": "fighting infection and disease"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these cities in brazil has hosted the olympic games",
        "answer": "rio de janeiro"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which year did alexander fleming discover penicillin",
        "answer": "1928"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following countries is located entirely in the northern hemisphere",
        "answer": "none of these answers are correct"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these countries does the prime meridian pass through",
        "answer": "mali"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following accurately describes the arctic circle",
        "answer": "polar day and polar night are phenomenons that occur there"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of matilda of flanders skills",
        "answer": "celtic blood"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of mulans skills",
        "answer": "indomitable army"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country was the first to invent perfume",
        "answer": "cyprus"
    },
    {
        "question": "whats the primary cause of the formation of the himalayas",
        "answer": "collision between plates"
    },
    {
        "question": "in greek mythology what is the goddess eos known as",
        "answer": "goddess of the dawn"
    },
    {
        "question": "which god is taranis in celtic mythology",
        "answer": "thunder god"
    },
    {
        "question": "during chinas warring states period which state defeated the other six and built the unified chinese empire",
        "answer": "qin"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the primary cause of karst landforms",
        "answer": "the dissolution of soluble rocks"
    },
    {
        "question": "the bastille a prison once located in the center of paris france originally served what purpose",
        "answer": "defensive fortress"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following doctors was the first to describe completely and in detail the systemic circulation and the function of the heart",
        "answer": "william harvey"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country was marco polo a famous explorer and merchant born in",
        "answer": "republic of venice"
    },
    {
        "question": "where was the world heritage terracotta army found",
        "answer": "in a royal mausoleum"
    },
    {
        "question": "karst landform cause",
        "answer": "dissolution of soluble rocks"
    },
    {
        "question": "which one of these animals does not lay eggs",
        "answer": "bat"
    },
    {
        "question": "apart from times you can be helped and power which of the following alliance center parameters can also be upgraded",
        "answer": "reinforcement troop capacity"
    },
    {
        "question": "apart from number of scouts and power which of the following scout camp parameters can also be upgraded",
        "answer": "scout march speed and exploration range"
    },
    {
        "question": "what does alliance skill natures gift do",
        "answer": "summon resources point in a selected area cannot be used in the lost kingdom"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these two were created by leonardo da vinci",
        "answer": "the last supper mona lisa"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the root cause of altitude sickness",
        "answer": "rapid exposure to low amounts of oxygen at high elevation"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following buildings cannot be upgraded",
        "answer": "courier station"
    },
    {
        "question": "what does alliance skill fully loaded do",
        "answer": "increases alliance members gathering speed for one type of resource"
    },
    {
        "question": "which technology comes before swordsman",
        "answer": "iron working"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following best describes a clownfish",
        "answer": "tropical marine fish"
    },
    {
        "question": "which technology comes before pavise",
        "answer": "bodkin arrows"
    },
    {
        "question": "which technology comes right before heavy cavalry",
        "answer": "scale armor"
    },
    {
        "question": "in ancient egypt which of the following was not a privilege of being a scribe",
        "answer": "exempt from paying medical expenses if sick"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following wasnt a benefit from being a scribe of ancient egypt",
        "answer": "except from medical paid sick lead"
    },
    {
        "question": "how was the gutenberg bible put into mass production",
        "answer": "movable type printing press"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which year was the napoleonic code established",
        "answer": "1804"
    },
    {
        "question": "which dutch scientist is know as the father of microbiology",
        "answer": "antonie van leeuwenhoek"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which country was the famed revolutionary and military strategist simn bolvar born",
        "answer": "venezuela"
    },
    {
        "question": "where is the capital of scotland",
        "answer": "edinburgh"
    },
    {
        "question": "since its founding in 1863 how many times has the international comittee of the red cross won the nobel peace prize",
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "the novel romance of the three kingdoms begins near the end of which chinese dynsasty",
        "answer": "han"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which theater was beethovens symphony no5 in c minor debuted in 1808",
        "answer": "the theater and der wien"
    },
    {
        "question": "in morse code what is the length in dots between two words",
        "answer": "7"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the last emperor of the holy roman empire",
        "answer": "francis ii"
    },
    {
        "question": "after a venus flytrap catches an insect how does it digest and absorb the prey",
        "answer": "the inner flaps of the leaves secrete a digestive fluid"
    },
    {
        "question": "of the following which is most likely to have directly led to the bronze age",
        "answer": "bronze is harder and more durable than other metals available at the time"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is an economic building",
        "answer": "alliance center"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following awards daily activity points",
        "answer": "defeating barbarian troops on the map"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following cities was the first to have an underground rapid transit system",
        "answer": "london"
    },
    {
        "question": "why was british nurse florence nightingale known as the lady with the lamp",
        "answer": "she would inspect patients at night"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the first king of italy after its unification in 1861",
        "answer": "victor emmanuel ii"
    },
    {
        "question": "which title did pierre de coubertin founder of the international olympic committee hold",
        "answer": "baron"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which year was the first wimbledon tennis championship held",
        "answer": "1877"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is the worlds first national park",
        "answer": "yellowstone national park"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which country was carlsberg group a leading brewer founded in 1847",
        "answer": "denmark"
    },
    {
        "question": "whats does the skillful craftsman alliance skill do when used",
        "answer": "greatly increases alliance flag construction speed"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many reward chests are awarded for reaching 60 daily activity points",
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following structures is a military building",
        "answer": "scout camp"
    },
    {
        "question": "what are the dimensions of the fog cleared by a kingdom map item",
        "answer": "10x10"
    },
    {
        "question": "what caused the death of pericles",
        "answer": "a plague"
    },
    {
        "question": "what are the windshaped cones of tornadoes famous for",
        "answer": "spinning"
    },
    {
        "question": "how long does the item builder recruitment last",
        "answer": "2 days"
    },
    {
        "question": "at which vip level do you permanently unlock a second building queue",
        "answer": "level 6"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many times can you receive alliance help if your alliance center is level 25",
        "answer": "30"
    },
    {
        "question": "during which emperors reign was the roman colosseum completed",
        "answer": "titus"
    },
    {
        "question": "elder brother of zeus",
        "answer": "poseidon"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the default rallied troop capacity when your castle is level 25",
        "answer": "2 million"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many separate khanates or empires had the mongol empire fractured into by the time of kublais death in 1294",
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "who initiated the first salt march",
        "answer": "mahatma gandhi"
    },
    {
        "question": "held in 1929 how long did the first academy awards oscars ceremony take",
        "answer": "15 minutes"
    },
    {
        "question": "the zeppelin was invented by engineers from which country",
        "answer": "germany"
    },
    {
        "question": "on its tragic maiden voyage what was the titanics intended destination",
        "answer": "new york"
    },
    {
        "question": "what did theodorus van gogh the younger brother of famed dutch painter vincent van gogh do for a living",
        "answer": "art dealer"
    },
    {
        "question": "in what year did einstein publish his four annus mirabilis miracle papers",
        "answer": "1905"
    },
    {
        "question": "which two oceans does the panama canal connect",
        "answer": "the pacific and atlantic oceans"
    },
    {
        "question": "for which disease did edward jenner known as the father of immunology develop a vaccine",
        "answer": "smallpox"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a decorative building",
        "answer": "stone drum"
    },
    {
        "question": "what was belisarius nickname",
        "answer": "the last of romans"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many vip points can you buy with 200 gems",
        "answer": "200"
    },
    {
        "question": "what caused the death of the outstanding statesmen and military strategist pericles",
        "answer": "a plague"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is most likely to have directly led to the bronze age",
        "answer": "bronze is harder and more durable than other metals available at the time"
    },
    {
        "question": "which pharaoh ordered the construction of the abu simbel temples",
        "answer": "ramesses ii"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following did not occur during the grecopersian wars",
        "answer": "the battle of agincourt"
    },
    {
        "question": "which script was the code of hammurabi engraved onto stone in",
        "answer": "cuneiform"
    },
    {
        "question": "according to the tale of the shewolf in roman mythology what came of the twins she nurtured romulus and remus",
        "answer": "romulus became the founder and the first king of rome"
    },
    {
        "question": "which modernday city was shakespeares globe theater built in",
        "answer": "london"
    },
    {
        "question": "how much will an enhanced attack advanced item increase your attack",
        "answer": "10"
    },
    {
        "question": "what were the men and women hiding from on the outskirts of florence in the novella collection the decameron",
        "answer": "the black plague"
    },
    {
        "question": "what was the famous speech by otto von bismarck regarding in 1862",
        "answer": "blood and iron"
    },
    {
        "question": "why was the dead sea given this name",
        "answer": "the highsaline water prevents plants and animals from thriving near it"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the only us president that served more than 2 terms",
        "answer": "franklin d roosevelt"
    },
    {
        "question": "what does the word formua in formula 1 racing refer to",
        "answer": "the rules which participating cars must follow"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the worlds oldest film festival",
        "answer": "venice film festival"
    },
    {
        "question": "edward viii became king of england in january 1936 later in the same year in which month did he give up the throne",
        "answer": "december"
    },
    {
        "question": "who initiated the first salt march",
        "answer": "mahatma gandhi"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the first astronaut to enter outer space",
        "answer": "yuri gagarin"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following were born in the same year as singer luciano pavarotti",
        "answer": "elvis presley"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which uk city were the beatles founded in 1960",
        "answer": "liverpool"
    },
    {
        "question": "edward viii became king of england in january 1936 later in the same year in which month did he give up the throne",
        "answer": "december"
    },
    {
        "question": "which script was the code of hammurabi engraved onto stone in",
        "answer": "cuneiform"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander showed their military genius in the battle of tours in the 8th century ad",
        "answer": "charles martel"
    },
    {
        "question": "according to the tale of the shewolf in roman mythology what came of the twins she nurtured romulus and remus",
        "answer": "romulus became the founder and first king of rome"
    },
    {
        "question": "what were the men and women hiding from on the outskirts of florence in the novella collection the decameron",
        "answer": "the black plague"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following speeches was made by the prussian prime minister otto von bismarck in september of 1862",
        "answer": "blood and iron"
    },
    {
        "question": "which civilization gives a 5 attack bonus to cavalry units",
        "answer": "germany"
    },
    {
        "question": "how much will an enhanced gathering item increase your gathering speed",
        "answer": "50"
    },
    {
        "question": "the novel romance of the three kingdoms begins near the end of which chinese dynasty",
        "answer": "han"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the founder of the edo bakufu of japan",
        "answer": "tokugawa ieyasu"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the duration of the builder recruitment item",
        "answer": "2 days"
    },
    {
        "question": "which modernday city was shakespeares globe theater built in",
        "answer": "london"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following stories is not one of grimms fairy tale",
        "answer": "the little mermaid"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the first woman to win a nobel prize",
        "answer": "marie curie"
    },
    {
        "question": "which chinese dynasty did jiang ziya help to establish",
        "answer": "the zhou dynasty"
    },
    {
        "question": "which two cities does portugals dom luis bridge connect",
        "answer": "porta vila nova de gaia"
    },
    {
        "question": "what was the original purpose of the great pyramid of giza",
        "answer": "pharoah khufus tomb"
    },
    {
        "question": "which if the following buffs can take effect during sunset canyon battles",
        "answer": "buffs from equipment"
    },
    {
        "question": "what was the regnal name of the last emperor of chinas qing dynasty",
        "answer": "xuantong"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following works is based on the battle of roncevaux pass fought by charlemagne and his knights",
        "answer": "the song of roland"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the only known shortperiod comet that is regularly visible to the naked eye from earth",
        "answer": "halleys comet"
    },
    {
        "question": "in norse mythology who does the hammer mjolnir belong to",
        "answer": "thor"
    },
    {
        "question": "which philosopher wrote utopia",
        "answer": "plato"
    },
    {
        "question": "lactose intolerance is caused by a shortage of what",
        "answer": "lactase"
    },
    {
        "question": "why were the bow and stern of viking longboats designed to be symmetrical",
        "answer": "to reverse direction quickly without a turn around"
    },
    {
        "question": "in 1998 the 16th fifa world cup was held in which country",
        "answer": "france"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country is catalhoyuk atalhyk located in",
        "answer": "turkey"
    },
    {
        "question": "in ark of osiris how many teleports does the first alliance to occupy an obelisk earn",
        "answer": "8"
    },
    {
        "question": "french national day is on july 14 in order to coincide with which historical event",
        "answer": "storming of the bastille"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not a natural resource",
        "answer": "clothes"
    },
    {
        "question": "the throwing axeman is which civilizations special unit",
        "answer": "france"
    },
    {
        "question": "elbe day was the meeting of which two armies during world war ii",
        "answer": "usa ussr"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was written by mary shelley",
        "answer": "frankenstein"
    },
    {
        "question": "who were the first mountaineers on record to reach the summit of mteverest",
        "answer": "tenzing norgay and edmund hilary"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the default transportation capacity if your trading post is level 25",
        "answer": "5 million"
    },
    {
        "question": "broccoli is rich in which vitamin",
        "answer": "vitamin c"
    },
    {
        "question": "which school of thought was founded by the chinese philosopher lao tzu",
        "answer": "taoism"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which continent did the serval first live",
        "answer": "africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "who gave the famous i have a dream speech",
        "answer": "martin luther king jr"
    },
    {
        "question": "in rok the throwing axeman is which civilizations special unit",
        "answer": "france"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following was written by mary shelley",
        "answer": "frankenstein"
    },
    {
        "question": "national emblem of ireland",
        "answer": "harp"
    },
    {
        "question": "during which season are nights relatively short and days relatively long",
        "answer": "summer"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following civilizations increase the damage of active commander skills by 5",
        "answer": "ottomans"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which gallery is the mona lisa currently held",
        "answer": "the louvre"
    },
    {
        "question": "who authored the novel no longer human",
        "answer": "osamu dazai"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is the god of love in norse mythology",
        "answer": "freyja"
    },
    {
        "question": "the american dream is rooted in which of these documents",
        "answer": "the declaration of independence"
    },
    {
        "question": "the independence march is the national anthem of which country",
        "answer": "turkey"
    },
    {
        "question": "which school of painting would georges seurat be a representative of",
        "answer": "pointillism"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which english palace did the star chamber sit",
        "answer": "palace of westminster"
    },
    {
        "question": "edward viii became king of england in january 1936 later in the same year in which month did he give up the throne",
        "answer": "december"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these active skills belongs to charles martel",
        "answer": "immortal shield"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which year was the first edition of the diary of anne frank published",
        "answer": "1947"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which country was the microscope invented",
        "answer": "the netherlands"
    },
    {
        "question": "darwins las book primarily discussed which species influence on soil",
        "answer": "earthworms"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many olympic gold medals did africanamerican jesse owens win in 1936",
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "in norse mythology what variety of trees was the world tree",
        "answer": "ash"
    },
    {
        "question": "the el nino phenomenon is named after which of these festivals",
        "answer": "christmas"
    },
    {
        "question": "tongwancheng was the capital of which ethnic group from ancient china",
        "answer": "the xiongnu"
    },
    {
        "question": "charles macintosh crafted a very early version of a raincoat from which material",
        "answer": "rubber"
    },
    {
        "question": "a decrease in which of the following metrics might indicate increasing nearness to a state of vacuum",
        "answer": "air pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "what two countries together made up the iberian union",
        "answer": "portugal and spain"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these navigators was the first european to arrive in brazil",
        "answer": "pedro alvares cabral"
    },
    {
        "question": "which city defeated sparta in the battle of leuctra",
        "answer": "thebes"
    },
    {
        "question": "to which army did the varangian guard belong",
        "answer": "the byzantine army"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following commanders was effectively the ruler of their kingdom but never officially the head of state",
        "answer": "charles martel"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these items can not be purchased within the mysterious merchants boutique",
        "answer": "passport page"
    },
    {
        "question": "how long does the basic army expansion boost last",
        "answer": "4h"
    },
    {
        "question": "which civilization offers increased hospital capacity",
        "answer": "byzantine"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these is not considered one of the five good emperors of the nervaantonine dynasty of ancient rome",
        "answer": "commodus"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which region was the empire of srivijaya located",
        "answer": "southeast asia"
    },
    {
        "question": "who wrote the opera carmen",
        "answer": "georges bizet"
    },
    {
        "question": "the concept of separation of powers comes from which work by montesquieu",
        "answer": "the spirit of law"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which year was the battle of guandu",
        "answer": "200"
    },
    {
        "question": "whose victory was the orchestral work 1812 overture composed to ommemorate",
        "answer": "russian empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which country was the somme the most infamous battlefield in world war i located",
        "answer": "france"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the leader of the western army during the battle of sekigahara which took place during japans sengoku period",
        "answer": "ishida mitsunari"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the book of exodus who leads the jewish people to the promised land",
        "answer": "moses"
    },
    {
        "question": "who did boudica lead the tribes of britain in a revolt against",
        "answer": "the holy roman empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country did the famous poet dante alighieri come from",
        "answer": "italy"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the nationality of pierre de fermat who proposed fermats last theorem",
        "answer": "france"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many years are there between each winter olympic games",
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "the golden bear award is given out at which film festival",
        "answer": "berlin film festival"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these buildings is not one of the new seven wonders of the world",
        "answer": "the palace of versailles"
    },
    {
        "question": "who wrote the wellknown science fiction series dune",
        "answer": "frank herbert"
    },
    {
        "question": "what outstanding contribution to science won biologist karl landsteiner the nobel prize",
        "answer": "discovering the human blood groups"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these effect is not caused by aethelflaeds skills",
        "answer": "healing slightly wounded units"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not a suit in poker",
        "answer": "winds"
    },
    {
        "question": "in ancient greek mythology who was hermes father",
        "answer": "zeus"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following inventions did not come about during the first industrial revolution",
        "answer": "telephone"
    },
    {
        "question": "who founded the spanish armada",
        "answer": "philip ii"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the main ingredient in salt",
        "answer": "sodium chloride"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was platos teacher",
        "answer": "socrates"
    },
    {
        "question": "the greek alphabet originated from which other writing system",
        "answer": "phoenician"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commanders active skill can inflict silence",
        "answer": "hermann"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is the correct description for the stratosphere",
        "answer": "it is warm above and cold below"
    },
    {
        "question": "what useful tool did famed carpenter lu ban invent",
        "answer": "the saw"
    },
    {
        "question": "pandas have 5 clawed toes on as well as a sixth digit what do pandas use their sixth digit for",
        "answer": "to hold bamboo while eating"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the capital of the republic of chile",
        "answer": "santiago"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the below figures were not knights of king arthurs round table",
        "answer": "merlin"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these is not an ancient civilization of the americas",
        "answer": "the sumerians"
    },
    {
        "question": "how long did the hundred years war last",
        "answer": "116 years"
    },
    {
        "question": "which artist painted the worldfamous girl with a pearl earring",
        "answer": "johannes vermeer"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country did zarathustra of the tone poem thus spoke zarathustra come from",
        "answer": "persia"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following works was written by the french playwright pierre corneille",
        "answer": "le cid"
    },
    {
        "question": "in ancient greek mythology who was the wife of hades the king of the underworld",
        "answer": "persephone"
    },
    {
        "question": "in rok the hwarang is which civilizations special unit",
        "answer": "korea"
    },
    {
        "question": "the saying the empire on which the sun never sets was originally used in reference to which countrys empire",
        "answer": "spain"
    },
    {
        "question": "what can masonry technology help you to improve",
        "answer": "the building speed of buildings in your city"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is a military building",
        "answer": "scout camp"
    },
    {
        "question": "who wrote the wellknown book sapiens a brief history of humankind",
        "answer": "yuval noah harari"
    },
    {
        "question": "where did reggae music originate",
        "answer": "jamaica"
    },
    {
        "question": "the phoenician civilization originated in which part of the world",
        "answer": "the eastern mediterranean"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these commanders gets the ability to convert some slain units into severely wounded units when attacking a city",
        "answer": "charlemagne"
    },
    {
        "question": "what animal is the tigris named after in ancient greek",
        "answer": "tiger"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these countries did not participate in the northern seven years war15631570",
        "answer": "the united kingdom"
    },
    {
        "question": "which is the smallest known snake species",
        "answer": "barbados threadsnake"
    },
    {
        "question": "who founded the malacca sultanate",
        "answer": "parameswara"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is known as the immortal hammer",
        "answer": "charles martel"
    },
    {
        "question": "where did the final battle between king arthur and mordred take place according to arthurian legend",
        "answer": "camlann"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is nicknamed bow of revolution",
        "answer": "yi seong gye"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many troops can governors send with a level 17 city hall or above",
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these alliance officers bestows a research speed boost",
        "answer": "counsellor"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many letters are used in todays version of english",
        "answer": "26"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following civilizations cannot buff their cavalry",
        "answer": "the ottomans"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these items can not be obtained by defeating barbarians",
        "answer": "vip points"
    },
    {
        "question": "which year was soviet union established",
        "answer": "1922"
    },
    {
        "question": "who led kingdom of the vandals and alans in vandalic war",
        "answer": "belisarius"
    },
    {
        "question": "who came out the victor of the battle of hastings",
        "answer": "william the conqueror"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these is the national flower of india",
        "answer": "lotus"
    },
    {
        "question": "the dragonfly cutter was the weapon of choice of which legendary warrior",
        "answer": "honda tadakatsu"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is the patron and protector of athens in ancient greek mythology",
        "answer": "athena"
    },
    {
        "question": "who owns easter island",
        "answer": "chile"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not a low country of europe",
        "answer": "the united kingdoms"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is the mother of cupid the babyfaced god of love in roman mythology",
        "answer": "venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "where was pablo picasso born",
        "answer": "iberia"
    },
    {
        "question": "when were bicycles introduced to europe",
        "answer": "the 19th century"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is reputed to have said i came i saw i conquered",
        "answer": "julius cesar"
    },
    {
        "question": "which unit gains a strong benefit from sun tzus master strategist skill",
        "answer": "infantry"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these commanders gets the ability to convert some slain units",
        "answer": "charlemagne"
    },
    {
        "question": "who defeated the sphinx according to greek legend",
        "answer": "oedipus"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these alliance officers bestows a research speed boost",
        "answer": "counsellor"
    },
    {
        "question": "who wrote human all too human",
        "answer": "nietzsche"
    },
    {
        "question": "in rok the cataphract is which civilizations special unit",
        "answer": "byzantium"
    },
    {
        "question": "where was napoleon bonaparte exiled after his defeat at waterloo",
        "answer": "st helena"
    },
    {
        "question": "which demigod captures cerberus the threeheaded hound of hades according to greek mythology",
        "answer": "hercules"
    },
    {
        "question": "which state is home to the walt disney company",
        "answer": "california"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the name of the turkish straits that divide europe from asia",
        "answer": "the bosphorus"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the most abundant element in the earths crust",
        "answer": "oxygen"
    },
    {
        "question": "who wrote the symposium",
        "answer": "plato"
    },
    {
        "question": "the military leader charles martel was not known for which of the following",
        "answer": "leading cavalry units"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many daily activity points do you need in lucerne scrolls to claim the daily gift clue reward",
        "answer": "50"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of matilda of flanders skills",
        "answer": "celtic blood"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is the god of war in ancient greek mythology",
        "answer": "ares"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the largest animal on the planet",
        "answer": "blue whale"
    },
    {
        "question": "when did the war of austrian succession take place",
        "answer": "1740  1748"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is the god of death in ancient greek mythology",
        "answer": "thanatos"
    },
    {
        "question": "the pantheon has been the burial site of many important artists since the renaissance which of the following artists were buried there",
        "answer": "raphael"
    },
    {
        "question": "in which country were instant noodles first invented",
        "answer": "japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "which is the deepest known trench in the world",
        "answer": "the mariana trench"
    },
    {
        "question": "which is the longest continental mountain range on earth",
        "answer": "the andes"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following technologies precedes horsemanship",
        "answer": "military discipline"
    },
    {
        "question": "which military commander was known as teutoburgs liberator",
        "answer": "hermann"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is a light year a measure of",
        "answer": "distance"
    },
    {
        "question": "the colossus of rhodes depicts which god of the sun",
        "answer": "helios"
    },
    {
        "question": "which composer wrote the opera the ring of the nibelung",
        "answer": "wagner"
    },
    {
        "question": "what was the original purpose of the great pyramid of giza",
        "answer": "pharaoh khufus tomb"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is julius caesars nickname",
        "answer": "the uncrowned king"
    },
    {
        "question": "who designed the ottoman cannon",
        "answer": "urban"
    },
    {
        "question": "which country was england fighting during the battle of agincourt",
        "answer": "france"
    },
    {
        "question": "what did che guevara study in college",
        "answer": "medicine"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is responsible for ushering valiant warriors into valhalla upon death in norse mythology",
        "answer": "valkyrie"
    },
    {
        "question": "who wrote the wellknown book a brief history of time",
        "answer": "stephen hawking"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these nobel prizes was awarded to marie curie in 1903",
        "answer": "the nobel prize in physics"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these countries is not a founding member of nato in 1949",
        "answer": "turkey"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these works of japanese monogatari literature describes the legend of kaguyahime",
        "answer": "the tale of the bamboo cutter"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the followong is not one of baybars skills",
        "answer": "thunderous force"
    },
    {
        "question": "the day of the tiles is regarded by some historians to mark the beginning of the french revolution in what city did it take place",
        "answer": "grenoble"
    },
    {
        "question": "what benefit does researching mathematics in the academy provide",
        "answer": "increased research speed"
    },
    {
        "question": "who was the first consul of the roman republic",
        "answer": "lucius junius brutus"
    },
    {
        "question": "which continent was the birthplace of mayan civilization",
        "answer": "the americas"
    },
    {
        "question": "who led the kingdom of prussia in the seven years war",
        "answer": "frederick ii"
    },
    {
        "question": "which musician composed the marriage of figaro",
        "answer": "mozart"
    },
    {
        "question": "hieroglyphs were part of which countrys formal writing system",
        "answer": "ancient egypt"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these is one of minamoto no yoshitunes active skill",
        "answer": "kyohachiryu"
    },
    {
        "question": "which commander is commonly regarded as having exemplified the ideal of the bushido spirit",
        "answer": "kusunoki masashige"
    },
    {
        "question": "which ancient egyptian pharaos tomb did british archaeologist howard carter discover in 1992",
        "answer": "tutankhamun"
    },
    {
        "question": "how often is the fifa world cup held",
        "answer": "every 4 years"
    },
    {
        "question": "queen guinevere fell in love with which knight of the round table according to arthurian legend",
        "answer": "lancelot"
    },
    {
        "question": "cactus spines are actually a modified form of which other part of the plant",
        "answer": "leaves"
    },
    {
        "question": "equipment with special talent bonuses will have their attributes enhanced by what percentage when equipped to a commander with the corresponding talent",
        "answer": "30"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these artists was not a baraque painter",
        "answer": "vincent van gogh"
    },
    {
        "question": "the 1000 point achievement chests includes",
        "answer": "epic commander sculpture"
    },
    {
        "question": "machu picchu is a notable relic of which civilization",
        "answer": "the incas"
    },
    {
        "question": "which artist is buried at the pantheon",
        "answer": "raphael"
    },
    {
        "question": "who kills odin the king of the gods during ragnarok in norse mythology",
        "answer": "fenrir"
    },
    {
        "question": "how many items of the same quality should i equip to complete ready for battle",
        "answer": "6"
    },
    {
        "question": "in the commander view page  what buff do commanders acting as a bloodfist guard get",
        "answer": "1 troop health"
    },
    {
        "question": "in what country did the battle of marengo take place",
        "answer": "italy"
    },
    {
        "question": "which emperor was named the khan of heaven by various turkic nomads during the sui and tang dynasties",
        "answer": "emperor taizong of tang"
    },
    {
        "question": "the battle of las navas de tolosa was a major turning point in which conflict",
        "answer": "the reconquista"
    },
    {
        "question": "who founded the first persian empire",
        "answer": "cyrus the great"
    },
    {
        "question": "in what era of chinese history did the battle of fei river take place where a small number of soldiers conquered a vastly superior force",
        "answer": "the eastern jin dynasty"
    },
    {
        "question": "what race of creatures mythical or otherwise lived on asgard according to norse myth",
        "answer": "aesir"
    },
    {
        "question": "turkish strait crisis divide europe and asia",
        "answer": "bosporus"
    },
    {
        "question": "who founded the kamakura shogunate",
        "answer": "minamoto no yoritomo"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following is not one of the fates of norse mythology",
        "answer": "karma"
    },
    {
        "question": "the epic poem of el cid originated from which country",
        "answer": "spain"
    },
    {
        "question": "legendary commander of the joseon dynasty yi sunsin sacrificed his life in which famous battle",
        "answer": "battle of noryang"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these is an incorrect description of the battle of poitiers",
        "answer": "the campaign took place during world war i"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these is an incorrect description of the mare imbrium on the moon",
        "answer": "it contains a certain amount of sedimentary water"
    },
    {
        "question": "who is the first italian to receive the pritzker architecture prize",
        "answer": "aldo rossi"
    },
    {
        "question": "what is the name of the turkish straits that divide europe from asia",
        "answer": "the strait of gibraltar"
    },
    {
        "question": "who founded the malacca sultanate",
        "answer": "parameswara"
    }
]